Register of the Uncommon Knowledge Video Tapes
Hoover Institution Archives
- Individual Program Descriptions, 1996-2010 (Folder 1-60, 62-126, on shelf)
  - Series 600, 2001-2002
    - "Educating by Numbers: Standards, Testing, and Accountability in Education" No. UK632, 2002 January 9 (Folder VHS, box 12; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 76)
      Williamson Evers, research fellow, Hoover Institution and member, Hoover-Koret Task Force on K-12 education; and Elliot Eisner, professor of education, Stanford University. Will standards-based testing and accountability improve our nation's education system? In January 2002, President Bush signed into law the Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 2002. The act calls for a mandatory annual test in reading and math for every child in the nation in the third through eighth grades. Schools that fail to improve their students' scores may be held accountable, possibly losing some federal funding. Supporters of the act say that standards-based testing and accountability are the best ways to monitor and improve the nation's schools. Opponents say that such a regime is largely a political ploy that will do more harm than good. Who's right?
    - "Future Shock: High Technology and the Human Prospect" No. UK633, 2001 December 7 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 77)
      Bill Joy, chief scientist, Sun Microsystems, and Ray Kurzwell, author, The Age of Spiritual Machines and founder and CEO, Kurzweil Technologies. Computers more important than humans? Self-replicating molecular robots? Virtual immortality? These may sound like science fiction, but some reputable computer scientists are predicting they will happen within the next several decades. What will our world be like if and when our machines surpass us in our intelligence? Do the advances in biotechnology, robotics, and nanotechnology, which make intelligent machines possible, pose dangers of their own? Should we embrace such a future or try to stop it?
    - "Darwin under the Microscope: Questioning Darwinism" No. UK634, 2001 December 7 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 77)
      William Dembski, fellow, Discovery Institute, and author, Mere Creation: Science, Faith, and Intelligent Design, and Eugenie Scott, executive director, National Center for Science Education. More than 140 years after Charles Darwin published On the Origin of Species, his theory of evolution is still generating controversy. Although Darwinism is championed by the majority of the scientific community, some have claimed that Darwin's theory is bad science and have put forward their own even more controversial theories. What should we make of these arguments? Is one such theory, known as intelligent design, merely creationism by another name, or is it a legitimate scientific alternative to Darwinism?
    - "In Whose Image? Evolution and Spirituality" No. UK635, 2001 December 7 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 77)
      William Dembski, fellow, Discovery Institute and author, Mere Creation: Science, Faith, and Intelligent Design; Robert Russell, director, Center for Theology and Natural Science; and Eugenie Scott, executive director, National Center for Science Education. Did life on earth unfold by chance or by design? According to the natural sciences and Darwin's theory of evolution, it was by chance. According to the Judeo-Christian tradition, it was by divine design. On this crucial question, science and religion appear to be irreconcilable. But are they? Does Darwinism encourage atheism? Must Christians be anti-Darwin?
    - "Test Tube America: Immigration" No. UK636, 2002 January 22 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 77)
      Michael Barone, media fellow, Hoover Institution and senior writer, U.S. News and World Report, and Peter Skerry, senior fellow, Brookings Institution, and professor of government, Claremont McKenna College. In 1965, Congress voted to change the laws that had restricted immigration into the United States for more than four decades. The Immigration Act of 1965 resulted in a wave of increased immigration that continues today. How do recent immigrant groups compare with those of the last great wave of immigration a century ago? Are they successfully integrating into American culture or threatening America's cultural stability? Should immigration once again be restricted, or should we concern ourselves with helping immigrants assimilate when they arrive?
    - "The Red and the Blue: The Cultural and Political Divide in America" No. UK637, 2002 January 22 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 78)
      Michael Barone, media fellow, Hoover Institution and senior writer, U.S. News and World Report; and Ruy Teixeira, senior fellow, Century Foundation, and coauthor, The Emerging Democratic Majority. Is America a divided nation? Sharp regional voting patterns were evident in the 2000 presidential election: rural, Midwestern, and southern voters went for Bush; urban and coastal voters went for Gore. These regional voting patterns have led some to describe America as one nation with two cultures. Is this an accurate way of looking at American society? Or is America divided along economic rather than cultural lines? Just how fundamental are these differences and what impact will they have on the American political landscape?
    - "Strength in Numbers: Race and the Census" No. UK638, 2002 February 22 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 78)
      Ward Connerly, chairman, American Civil Rights Coalition; and Ramona E. Douglass, member, Decennial Census Advisory Committee and director of media and public relations, Association of MultiEthnic Americans. Should the U.S. census stop collecting racial and ethnic data? The 2000 census asked Americans to identify themselves according to 126 possible racial and ethnic categories, up from just 5 categories in 1990. Movements are now afoot to add even more racial categories to the 2010 census. Does the Collection of all these data stand in the way of the creation of a truly color blind society? Should we drop questions of race from the census and other government forms? Or are these data critical tools in the ongoing fight to end inequality and discrimination?
    - "I, Spy: Fixing the CIA" No. UK639, 2002 April 1 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 78)
      Robert Baer, former case officer, Central Intelligence Agency and author, See No Evil: The True Story of a Ground Soldier in the CIA's War on Terrorism, and Greg Trevorton, senior policy analyst, RAND and author, Reshaping National Intelligence for an Age of Information. The Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) has a budget of about $3 billion and more than 16,000 employees working to identify and protect the United States from foreign threats. Yet the CIA failed to prevent the terrorist attacks of September 11, 2001. How come? Should the CIA have been able to foresee and prevent this sort of attack? Now that the cold war is over, is it time to abolish the CIA or reform it to respond to the new threat of terrorism? If reform is the answer, should the CIA put more emphasis on high technology or on placing agents on the field?
  - Series 700, 2002-2003
    - "Taking Liberties: Civil Liberties and National Security" No. UK701, 2001 April 18 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 78)
      Robert Higgs, senior fellow in political economy, Independent Institute and author, Crisis and Leviathan: Critical Episodes in the Growth of American Government, and Gore Vidal, author, Perpetual War for Perpetual Peace: How We Got To Be So Hated. Following the September 11 terrorist attacks, Congress passed and President Bush signed the USA Patriot Act--legislation intended to thwart the threat of domestic terrorism. Critics were quick to denounce USA Patriot as a dangerous expansion of government power at the expense of our civil liberties. Are the critics right? Or can we win the war on terrorism without sacrificing our civil liberties here at home? And what has the American experience in earlier crises, such as the Civil War and the two world wars, taught us about balancing national security and personal freedom?
    - "Enemies of the State: Why the U.S. Is Hated" No. UK702, 2002 April 18 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 38; Digital Betacam, box 79)
      Dinesh D'Souza, Robert and Karen Rishwain research fellow, Hoover Institution and author, What's So Great About America; Robert Higgs, senior fellow in political economy, Independent Institute and author, Crisis and Leviathan: Critical Episodes in the Growth of American Government; and Gore Vidal, author, Perpetual War for Perpetual Peace: How We Got To Be So Hated. In a 2002 Gallup poll conducted in ten Muslim nations, only 22 percent of the people questioned viewed the United States favorably. Why does the United States foster such hatred in the Islamic world in particular? Is it our foreign policy--our support of Israel and of repressive Arab regimes in the Middle East? Or is it our culture? Does globalization spread American values that are simply antithetical, thus disruptive, to the traditional Islamic view of society? Just what should we do to win this struggle for the hearts and minds of those who despise us around the world?
    - "The Pentagon Strikes Back: The Defense Budget" No. UK703, 2002 April 22 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 79)
      Thomas Donnelly, deputy executive director, Project for the New American Century and Cindy Williams, senior research fellow, security studies program, Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In his State of the Union speech in January 2002, President Bush promised to spend "whatever it costs to defend our country." That cost, according to Bush's proposed budget, would come to $378 billion in 2003, $48 billion more than in 2002, and the largest percent increase in defense spending since the Reagan era. Critics are saying that the proposed 2003 budget perpetuates the Pentagon's most inefficient weapons and spending habits, thereby delaying the true transformation of the military that is needed to protect America in the twenty-first century. Who's right, the Bush administration or its critics?
    - "For Richer or Poorer: The Marriage Problem" No. UK704, 2002 April 1 (Folder VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 79)
      Irwin Garfinkel, Mitchell I. Ginsberg professor of contemporary urban problems, Columbia University School of Social Work, and James Q. Wilson, member, Board of Overseers, Hoover Institution, and Ronald Reagan professor of public policy. Study after study has shown that married people are healthier and wealthier than unmarried people and that children raised in two-parent homes are generally more successful in life than those who aren't. And yet, according to the U.S. census, about half of all first marriages end in divorce. Additionally, since 1960 the percentage of children born out of wedlock has grown from single digits to 20 percent. What is going on? Is the decline in marriage a symptom of underlying cultural problems in modern America? Or is it misguided to focus on marriage rather than on the economic problems facing all low income families, whether married or not?
    - "Attention: Deficit Disorder: The Budget Deficit" No. UK705, 2002 June 27 (Folder VHS, box 13; VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 79)
      Alan Auerbach, Robert D. Burch professor of law and economics and director of the Center of Tax Policy and Public Finance, University of California, Berkeley; and Stephen Moore, contributing editor, National Review, senior fellow in economics, Cato Institute, and president, Club for Growth. Just two years ago, in the 2000 fiscal year, the annual federal budget had a surplus of $236 billion. Now the federal government is facing a budget deficit of more than $150 billion, possibly much more. And whereas during the presidential campaign of 2000, the candidates were debating how to spend trillions in expected future surpluses, the Congressional Budget Office is now projecting a cumulative $1 trillion deficit by 2011. What happened to the surplus, and what is to blame for the return of the deficit? Is it President Bush's tax cut? Or was it the recession of 2001 and the war on terrorism? In light of the deficit, what should we make of the President's budget plans?
    - "Cross Purposes: The Crusades" No. UK706, 2002 April 22 (Folder VHS, box 13; VHS, box 13; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 80)
      William Hamblin, professor of history, Brigham Young University and Thomas Madden, associate professor of history and department chair, Saint Louis University, and author, A Concise History of the Crusades. The Crusades happened almost a thousand years ago: why do they still provoke an argument? Osama Bin Laden has used them to attempt to rally the Islamic world to his cause; President Bush has called the war on terrorism a "crusade." But what is the truth about the crusades? Were they motivated by savage greed and intolerance or by pious idealism? Were they an unprovoked attack by the west on the Islamic world or a reaction to centuries of Islamic incursions? How should we understand the legacy of the crusades today, in a time of conflict between the west and radical Islamic terrorists?
    - "Hebrew Nationalists: Why the U.S. Supports Israel" No. UK707, 2002 June 14 (Folder VHS, box 14; VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 80)
      John Podhoretz, media fellow, Hoover Institution and columnist, New York Post; Steven Spiegel, professor of political science, University of California, Los Angeles; and Stephen Zunes, associate professor of politics and chair of the Peace and Justice Program, University of San Francisco, and author, Tinderbox: U.S. Middle East Policy and the Roots of Terrorism. Recent opinion polls show that the American public overwhelmingly wants the United States to avoid taking sides in the conflict in the Middle East. Yet members of Congress have been nearly unanimous in their support of Israel in its actions against the Palestinians. Just why is our government so steadfastly supportive of Israel? Does this support further our legitimate strategic interests in the Middle East? Or is it the result of domestic special interest politics?
    - "Winds of Change: Politics after Sept. 11" No. UK708, 2002 July 18 (Folder VHS, box 14; VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 80)
      Newt Gingrich, distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution, former Speaker, United States House of Representatives; Christopher Hitchens, author and journalist, and visiting professor of liberal studies, New School University; and Nelson Polsby, Heller professor of political science, University of California, Berkeley. The war on terrorism has created unique ideological challenges for both ends of the American political spectrum. Does the left, long opposed to the exercise of U.S. military power, risk irrelevance by opposing the war on terror? How does the libertarian wing of the right, long opposed to big government, respond to its expanding role in protecting our security? How has President Bush's conduct of the war on terrorism affected his chances for reelection in 2004?
    - "Words of War: What Kind of War Are We Fighting?" No. UK709, 2002 July 18 (Folder VHS, box 14; VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 80)
      Newt Gingrich, distinguished visiting fellow, Hoover Institution and former Speaker, United States House of Representatives; Christopher Hitchens, author and journalist, and visiting professor of liberal studies, New School University. What kind of war is the war on terrorism? Ordinarily wars are fought against proper nouns--against Germany during the Second World War or against the Soviet Union during the cold war, for example. Now we're being asked to fight a war against a common noun, terrorism. Just how accurate and useful is the phrase "war on terrorism?" Is this a war? And who exactly is the enemy--Al Qaeda? Al Qaeda plus all other terrorists around the world? Al Qaeda plus all other terrorists plus all the countries in which the terrorists operate? In other words, just how good a job are the president and the administration doing, not just in prosecuting the war but in defining the objectives?
    - "A Crisis of Faith: The Crisis in the Catholic Church" No. UK710, 2002 June 27 (Folder VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 81)
      Rod Dreher, senior writer, National Review; Fr. Joseph Fessio, S.J., chancellor, Ave Maria University; and Gary Wills, Pulitzer Prize-winning historian and author, Why I Am a Catholic. The year will be remembered as a difficult one for the Catholic Church in America. Sex abuse scandals and criticism of the Church's response to those scandals dominated the headlines for months. Sexual abuse is not the only subject creating controversy within Catholic circles. Other divisive matters include the role of women within the Church, gay priests, and the relation of American bishops to the Vatican. Is the Catholic Church in danger of losing its constituency in America? Are substantial reforms in the structure and teachings of the Catholic Church necessary? Or are reforms what got the Church in trouble in the first place?
    - "Continental Divides: Are Europe and America Parting Ways?" No. UK711, 2002 July 29 (Folder VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 81)
      Coit Blacker, deputy director and senior fellow, Institute for International Studies, Stanford University; Richard Falk, Albert G. Milbank professor of international law and practice, emeritus, and professor of politics and international affairs, emeritus, Woodrow Wilson School, Princeton University; and John O'Sullivan, editor-in-chief, United Press International. Throughout the latter half of the Twentieth Century, the United States and Western Europe seemed the staunchest of allies, united in NATO in defense against the common threat of the Soviet Union. With the end of the cold war and the loss of that common enemy, however, signs of emerging tensions have appeared in the friendship between America and Europe. How serious are the spats between Europe and the United States over issues such as the International Criminal Court, the conflict in the Middle East, and the U.S. conduct of the war on terrorism? With the formation of the European Union, Europe has become an economic rival to the United States. Will it become a political and military rival as well?
    - "Trading Places: Is Free Trade Faltering?" No. UK712, 2002 June 14 (Folder VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 81)
      Walden Bello, executive director, Focus on the Global South, and Jagdish Bhagwati, Arthur Lehman professor of economics and professor of political science, Columbia University, and author, Free Trade Today. According to a 1998 study by the Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development, over the last half century nations that have been more open to trade have experienced double the annual growth rate of those that have been closed. So why would any nation be opposed to free trade? But, in fact, many developing countries are skeptical of free trade--believing that the rules of global trade benefit the rich, developed north at the expense of the poor, developing south. Are the critics right? With even President Bush's commitment appearing to falter, is the drive to greater free trade in crisis?
    - "Prognosis Negative: Health Care System in Crisis" No. UK713, 2002 June 14 (Folder VHS, box 14; Digital Betacam, box 81)
      Alan M. Garber, M.D., Henry J. Kaiser, Jr., professor of medicine and director of the Center for Health Policy/Center for Primary Care and Outcomes Research, Stanford University; George Halvorson, chief executive officer, Kaiser Permanente; and Helen H. Schauffler, professor of health policy and director of the Center for Health and Public Policy Studies, University of California, Berkeley. Ten years ago, soaring health care costs prompted the Clinton administration to propose sweeping reforms to the health care system, including a substantial new role for the federal government. But the plan drafted under the guidance of first lady Hillary Clinton was defeated in Congress. A decade later, the problems with our health care system seem to have only gotten worse. In the recent economic downturn, millions lost their insurance along with their jobs, adding to the estimated 40 to 45 million Americans who have no medical insurance at all. Meanwhile the costs incurred by government and businesses to keep the rest of us covered are skyrocketing. Has the HMO model of health care that became predominant in the 1990s failed us? If so, what should replace it?
    - "Europe Swings: Why Is Europe Moving to the Right?" No. UK714, 2002 July 29 (Folder VHS, box 14; Digital Betacam, box 82)
      Christopher Hitchens, author, journalist, and visiting professor of liberal studies, New School University; and John O'Sullivan, editor-in-chief, United Press International. For decades, Western Europe has been known for its social democracies: large welfare states governed by a coalition of the political left and center. In recent years, however, this center-left coalition seems to have broken down. Conservative parties have come to power in a number of European countries, including Spain, Italy, France, and the Netherlands. Why has Europe moved to the right? Have a few specific issues, such as immigration and crime, driven European voters to the right? Are voters merely expressing a temporary frustration with the center-left coalition, or is the new conservative Europe here to stay?
    - "Culture Clash: A Talk with Hernando De Soto" No. UK715, 2002 April 22 (Folder VHS, box 14; Betacam SP, box 39; Digital Betacam, box 82)
      Hernando De Soto, founder and president, Institute for Liberty and Democracy and author, The Mystery of Capitalism: Why Capitalism Triumphs in the West and Fails Everywhere Else. In the west, capitalism reigns triumphant. Living standards, wealth, and technological development in the capitalist western countries surpass anything seen before in human history. But why has capitalism so obviously failed in most developing countries? Why are some saying that capitalism is in a state of crisis today in the third world? Does the success of capitalism depend on western cultural values that simply don't translate to the third world? Or can economic and political reforms, especially reform of property rights, enable developing countries to share the same fruits of capitalism and free enterprise that we enjoy in the west?
    - "Pope and Circumstance: The Legacy of Pope John Paul II" No. UK716, 2002 June 27 (Folder VHS, box 14; Digital Betacam, box 82)
      Rod Dreher, senior writer, National Review; Fr. Joseph Fessio, S.J., chancellor, Ave Maria University; and Gary Wills, Pulitzer Prize-winning historian and author, Why I Am a Catholic. In 1978, the Polish cardinal Karol Wojtyla was elected to the papacy of the Catholic Church, taking the name of John Paul II. In the twenty-four years since, Pope John Paul II has traveled more widely and held audiences for more people than any other pope in history. But beyond his long history and high profile, how will John Paul II be remembered? Will he be remembered more for his political impact--many say that he played a crucial role in the fall of communism in Eastern Europe--or for his ecclesiastical work? Just how well has John Paul II prepared the Catholic Church for the twenty-first century?
    - "Law and Order: Civil Liberties and the War on Terrorism" No. UK717, 2002 September 27 (Folder VHS, box 14; Digital Betacam, box 82)